To start this course on networking, let's
look at four basic groups of terms and definitions
you will want to know going forward.
This first involves internet versus intranet
versus extranet.
The internet is the world's largest public
network and offers many ways to connect to
a vast amount of information.
I am on the internet right now, looking at
a website, for example.
You may have also heard of the term intranet.
An intranet is a website that is internal
to a business and not seen by the public.
If you have an intranet and decide to allow
some members from outside an organization
into the intranet, you technically have an
extranet.
There are two basic types of networks for
people to know about: peer-to-peer and client-server.
Most home and small office networks are peer-to-peer
networks where there is no central device
managing and storing users, files, and folders.
In essence, every device on a peer-to-peer
network is its own server because every device
is responsible for managing access to its
own resources, which are mostly files and
folders.
On the other hand, a client-server network
is the type of network present in many medium
to large-sized businesses where a central
server hosts all the user accounts, devices,
and permissions for the users and devices.
Active Directory, for example, is the server
piece in a Windows-based client-server network.
There are three data transmission types to
know about with networking: unicast, multicast,
and broadcast.
In unicast, data is transmitted from one device
to another.
With multicast, one device transmits data
to a selected group of devices.
In broadcast, a device transmits data to every
other device on its network.
Finally, we have the network devices themselves.
In this course, you will learn about switches,
routers, cables, and cable types.
However, I want to highlight one type of device
now, and that is an Internet of Things or
IoT device.
An IoT device is a device that can be controlled
remotely, often through a smartphone app or
something similar.
For example, a thermostat that can be programmed
remotely using an app is a prime example of
an IoT device.